{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "A monument at this site erected by the United Daughters of the Confederacy was controversial for its depiction of the \"faithful slave,\" Heyward Shepherd. Before his execution, the leader of an event at this site noted that \"the crimes of this guilty land will never be purged away, but with Blood.\" By seizing arms at this site, the leader of the Pottawatomie Massacre hoped to spark a slave revolt. For ten points, name this West Virginia town where John Brown raided a federal arsenal.",
      "answer": "Harpers Ferry Armory, West Virginia"
    },
    {
      "question": "While on his way to participate in this activity, Charles VIII of France died by striking his head on a lintel door. Members of the Third Estate vowed \"not to separate and to reassemble wherever necessary, until the Constitution of the kingdom is established\" in an \"Oath\" named for the location of this activity during the French Revolution. The aviator Roland Garros names a stadium in Paris dedicated to, for ten points, what sport, whose best players compete at the French Open and Wimbledon?",
      "answer": "Tennis"
    },
    {
      "question": "The first woman to win this award earned a PhD in political science from UCLA but won this award by demonstrating successful management of common property. That woman, Elinor Ostrom, was later joined by the only other woman to win this prize, Esther Dufflo, who, along with her husband, won in 2019 for their experimental approach to alleviating global poverty. Ragnar Frisch and Jan Tinbergen were the first recipients of, for ten points, what prestigious global award in the field of social science?",
      "answer": [
        "Nobel Memorial Prize in Economic Sciences or Sveriges Riksbank Prize in Economic Sciences in Memory of Alfred Nobel,",
        "Economics in place of Economic Sciences"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this war, over 350 tribal forces were killed when Lord Chelmsford led his forces into Natal Province at the Battle of Rorke’s Drift. This war began when King Cetshwayo rejected an ultimatum from the High Commissioner, Sir Henry Bartle Frere, in 1879. This war is known for several particularly bloody battles, including a decisive British loss against a technologically inferior foe at the Battle of Isandlwana. For ten points, name this war that took place in modern-day South Africa.",
      "answer": "Anglo-Zulu War 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 2"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of the first modern arguments for this theory was advanced during the English Civil War by Thomas Hobbes in Leviathan. According to one work titled for this concept, man is \"born free and everywhere he is in chains.\" Espoused by Enlightenment thinkers such as Jean-Jacques Rousseau and John Locke, this concept is implicit in the United States Constitution. For ten points, what is this political theory suggesting that rulers derive their authority from the consent of the people?",
      "answer": "Social contract"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this state, Clark Kerr declined to expel student protestors belonging to the Mario Savio-led Free Speech movement. Allan Bakke [[BAHK-ee]] was denied entry to medical school in this state under an affirmative action policy upheld in a 1978 Supreme Court decision. In 2020, a judge ruled that this state’s university system can no longer use ACT and SAT scores as a factor in admissions. For ten points, what state’s public university system includes campuses at Irvine and Berkeley?",
      "answer": "California"
    },
    {
      "question": "The pro-democratic Cylon and Ninon helped expel this man from Crotone [[croh- TOH-nay]] after he helped defeat Sybaris. This man studied the relationship between string length and musical note pitch, devising the Harmony of the Spheres theory for the planets. This man banned eating fava beans, and one of his followers was killed for revealing the existence of irrational numbers. For ten points, name this Greek polymath whose namesake theory says a squared plus b squared equals c squared.",
      "answer": "Pythagoras of Samos"
    },
    {
      "question": "Inflation increased during this man’s reign due to his heavy borrowing from the Fugger family. This led to this man sponsoring an expedition to find the legendary city of El Dorado in modern Venezuela. This monarch passed the Edict of Worms, calling for the capture of Martin Luther. Francisco Pizarro and Hernan Cortés conquered the Incan and Aztec Empires respectively during this man’s reign. For ten points, name this Habsburg Holy Roman Emperor who ruled both Austria and Spain.",
      "answer": [
        "Charles V",
        "Carlos I",
        "Charles I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1838, W.W. Phelps and John Whitmer established Far West, Missouri based on this man’s design plan. This man died in 1844, when a mob stormed the Carthage, Illinois jail in which he was being held. This man claimed to have experienced a vision in 1823 in which an angel directed him to a buried book of golden plates, which he would later transcribe into his new church’s foundational book. For ten points, name this man, the founder of Mormonism and the Latter Day Saints movement.",
      "answer": "Joseph Smith 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 2"
    },
    {
      "question": "The man who led these events faced a personal excommunication from Pope Alexander VI and ultimately execution after a thorough investigation from Sebastian Maggi [[MAH-jee]]. The “Weepers” were supporters of these mass gatherings, and the artist Sandro Botticelli supposedly contributed many of his own works, particularly those including nudity, to these events. For ten points, name these events that culminated on February 7, 1497 when followers of Savonarola burned thousands of “sinful” objects.",
      "answer": "Bonfire of the Vanities 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 2"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This person nominated Harriet Miers to the Supreme Court, and under his administration, Scooter Libby was implicated in the Valerie Plame Affair. This president devised the No Child Left Behind Act. This man also landed on the USS Abraham Lincoln and gave the “Mission Accomplished” speech, despite the fact that the Iraq War was still being fought. This man declared, \"I can hear you\" when speaking to first responders while standing next to a fireman with a bull horn. For ten points, name this US president from Texas who faced 9/11.",
        "answer": [
          "George Walker Bush",
          "Bush 43"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "George W. Bush helped make Texas the leading producer of this form of energy. This type of energy is collected at locations like Los Vientos and Tehachapi Pass in large \"farms.\"",
        "answer": [
          "Wind power",
          "descriptive answers indicating power",
          "electricity produced by wind"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this war, the Glorioso survived attacks at the Azores and Cape Finisterre with millions of silver dollars on board. Sardinian forces defended Villafranca in this war, and George Townshend also blockaded Genoa. Fog and snow, as well as inexperience, did not stop Frederick the Great from winning at Mollwitz during this war. After this war ended with the Treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle, Prussia allied with Britain in the Diplomatic Revolution. For ten points, name this war that challenged Maria Theresa's right to inherit the Hapsburg Empire.",
        "answer": "War of the Austrian Succession"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The War of the Austrian Succession also saw the last command of troops in combat by a reigning British monarch when this king led his men at Dettingen.",
        "answer": "George II"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Peter Lawford and this man organized the Inaugural Gala for JFK, but he later changed parties and arranged the gala for Ronald Reagan in 1980. This man built the Cal Neva Lodge & Casino at Lake Tahoe and opened its Celebrity Room. Mikhail Gorbachev and Gennadi Gerasimov sarcastically named a doctrine for this man in which Warsaw Pact states gained independence. Genovese crime boss Willie Moretti was the godfather of, for ten points, what Italian-American singer, known as “Ol’ Blue Eyes”?",
        "answer": "Frank Sinatra"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Frank Sinatra won an Academy Award for this 1953 film about three US Army soldiers, played by Sinatra, Montgomery Clift, and Burt Lancaster, in the days prior to the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor.",
        "answer": "From Here to Eternity 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 2"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After bombs planted by a terrorist cell ignited in this province’s CN Railway, John Diefenbaker asked “Is this Ireland?” while on national television. This province successfully transitioned from Roman Catholic run health institutions to public healthcare during its “Quiet Revolution.” Only used during the World Wars, one Prime Minister revived the War Measures Act in this Canadian province during the 1970s October Crisis. For ten points, name this Francophone Canadian province with the city of Montreal.",
        "answer": "Quebec"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "When asked by the media what he would do to end the October Crisis in Quebec, this Canadian PM said “Just Watch Me.” He is the father of the current Canadian Prime Minister.",
        "answer": "Pierre Trudeau"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "To build the hydrogen bomb, this company built and operated the Savannah River Site. This company created a brochure called \"Farming with Dynamite\" which promoted using explosives to remove obstacles. This company began by making gunpowder at the Eleutherian Mills for the US Army. This company created the ozone layer-damaging chlorofluorocarbon Freon. Some of this company's products include a material for nonstick pans, Teflon, as well as the polymer Nylon. For ten points, name this Delaware-based chemical company.",
        "answer": [
          "E.I. DuPont de Nemours and Company",
          "DuPont de Nemours, Inc."
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2017, the original duPont company merged with this other chemical company that was boycotted during the Vietnam War for its production of napalm.",
        "answer": "The Dow Chemical Company"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A college without walls was named for this man in Mount Angel. Ferdinand Marcos gave this man an honorary doctorate at the Eastern University following a trip in which this man praised Marcos’s martial law. A group organized by this man was situated at The Forty Acres, and this man negotiated with Lionel Steinberg in the Coachella area of California. This man organized the Delano Grape Strike, and with Dolores Huerta, this man co-founded the National Farm Workers Association. For ten points, name this Mexican-American labor leader.",
        "answer": "César Chávez"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This is the rallying cry for the United Farm Workers which was created during one of Chávez's fasts. In English, it translates to \"Yes, we can.\"",
        "answer": "Sí, se puede 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 2"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was the second president of the Royal Academy, and his The Graces Unveiling Nature is displayed at the center of the Academy today. This artist depicted a man in a green top kneeling next to a man holding a ream of cloth in a painting set at Shackamaxon. This painter of Penn’s Treaty with the Indians depicted a muscular Native American resting his chin on his fist on the left side of a work set on a battlefield outside of Quebec City. For ten points, what American artist painted The Death of General Wolfe?",
        "answer": "Benjamin West"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A massive work by Benjamin West in a chapel in Greenwich depicts this Biblical apostle after a shipwreck at Malta.",
        "answer": [
          "Saint Paul the Apostle",
          "Saul of Tarsus"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Old Vineyards were attacked at this battle, and during this battle, the sun overcame the fog, allowing St. Hilaire's men to attack the heights. A general at this battle said, “One sharp blow and the war is over.” Artillery broke the ice at this battle, causing men to drown in the Satschan ponds. This battle featured an attack on the Pratzen Heights and led to the creation of the Confederation of the Rhine and the signing of the Treaty of Pressburg. Russians and Austrians lost to Napoleon in, for ten points, what 1805 battle?",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Austerlitz",
          "Battle of the Three Emperors"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This last Holy Roman Emperor lost at the battle of Austerlitz and subsequently married his daughter Marie Louise, Duchess of Parma, to Napoleon.",
        "answer": "Francis II"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "American Environmentalism",
      "prompt": "Name the…...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Society George Bird Grinnel founded named for a French-American bird watcher.",
          "answer": "National Audubon Society"
        },
        {
          "question": "Structures some Conservationists oppose, such as the Glen Canyon version on the Colorado River.",
          "answer": "Dam"
        },
        {
          "question": "April 22 celebration of the protection our planet, proposed by Gaylord Nelson.",
          "answer": "Earth Day"
        },
        {
          "question": "Scottish-American who preserved Yosemite and founded the Sierra Club.",
          "answer": "John Muir"
        },
        {
          "question": "Minnesota presidential candidate who the Sierra Club supported against Ronald Reagan in 1984.",
          "answer": "Walter \"Fritz\" Mondale"
        },
        {
          "question": "Reservoir in Yosemite over which Conservationists and Preservationists fought about the water supply.",
          "answer": "Hetch Hetchy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Supreme Court Justice who suggested that environmental objects like valleys can be granted personhood in the Morton case.",
          "answer": "William O. Douglas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ivy League school which operates the eBird program at its Lab of Ornithology in Sapsucker Woods.",
          "answer": "Cornell University 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 2"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "20th Century Finland",
      "prompt": "Name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Season which names a war between Finland and the USSR, stalemated in part due to cold weather.",
          "answer": "Winter War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Finnish capital which hosted the 1952 Winter Olympics.",
          "answer": "Helsinki"
        },
        {
          "question": "Russian tsar who lost control of Finland after the Bolshevik Revolution destabilized his regime.",
          "answer": "Nicholas II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nearby Baltic nation that was invaded by Finnish forces in the Kinship Wars.",
          "answer": "Estonia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Historical region of southeastern Finland that it was forced to cede to the USSR in 1940.",
          "answer": "Karelia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Red Army nickname for Finnish soldier Simo Häyhä [[HIGH-hah]] for his success as a sniper.",
          "answer": "The White Death"
        },
        {
          "question": "War fought by the Finns and Nazis in an effort to regain Finnish territory from the Soviets during World War Two.",
          "answer": "Continuation War"
        },
        {
          "question": "President of Finland during the Interim Peace, who was sentenced to ten years in prison for his involvement with the Axis.",
          "answer": "Risto Ryti ] 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 2"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Hamas",
      "prompt": "Name the…...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Holy Middle Eastern city where the predecessor of Hamas set up branches.",
          "answer": "Jerusalem"
        },
        {
          "question": "Islamic sect Hamas supports, as contrasted with Shia Islam.",
          "answer": "Sunni Islam"
        },
        {
          "question": "Strip of land bordering Egypt and Israel which Hamas governs.",
          "answer": "Gaza Strip"
        },
        {
          "question": "Weapons Hamas uses, defended from by Israel’s Iron Dome.",
          "answer": [
            "Rockets",
            "\"artillery shells,\" \"missiles,\" and other similar descriptive answers"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Egyptian organization from which Hamas stems, upon which Nasser cracked down.",
          "answer": "Muslim Brotherhood or Society of the Muslim Brothers"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hamas was formed after the first of these Palestinian uprisings against Israel that often involved civilians throwing projectiles.",
          "answer": "Intifada"
        },
        {
          "question": "Military wing of Hamas, as contrasted with the Dawah.",
          "answer": [
            "Izz ad-Din al-Qassam Brigades",
            "EQB"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1994 Massacre of Muslims by Baruch Goldstein, which prompted Hamas to start targeting civilians.",
          "answer": [
            "Cave of the Patriarchs Massacre or Ibrahimi Mosque Massacre",
            "or Hebron Massacre 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 2"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Corruption in this federal agency, abetted by the first female administrator of this agency, Anne Gorsuch, was uncovered in the early-1980’s. Members of this agency were taken hostage by protestors led by Lois Gibbs during the Love (20 pts)",
        "Canal Crisis. This agency was originally formed in response to fiascos like the waste-fueled fires on the Cuyahoga River. The publication of Rachel Carson’s (10 pts)",
        "Silent Spring was key to the movement that led to the Nixon administration’s creation of, for ten points, what federal agency intended to fight pollution?"
      ],
      "answer": "Environmental Protection Agency or EPA"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This union published the Hungarian newsletter Bérmunkás. Members of this union were charged with treason as the Sydney Twelve after the Tottenham Tragedy. \"Slim\" Evans, part of the On-To-Ottawa trek, was once a member of this group, which was housed in the Finnish (*) Labor Temple in Canada. This union made the Little Red Songbook and wrote songs like \"There'll Be Pie in the Sky.” Mother Jones and (*) Big Bill Haywood were among the founders of this group, which advocated \"one great union.\" For ten points, name this labor union of \"Wobblies.”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Industrial Workers of the World",
        "IWW",
        "Wobblies before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Born with the surname Gelbfisz, this man formed a partnership with Cecil B. DeMille in 1913 to produce feature-length motion pictures. This man battled Adolph Zukor for control over Paramount Pictures and lost, after which this man created his own film studio under a (20 pts)",
        "new surname. In 1946, the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences awarded this man the Thalberg Memorial Award for his contributions to the medium of (10 pts)",
        "film. For ten points, name this mogul from the Golden Age of Hollywood whose name contributes a letter to the film studio MGM."
      ],
      "answer": "Samuel Goldwyn"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the 1960s, this site was excavated by Yigael Yadin, who discovered 28 human remains and a number of bathhouses. Lucius Flavius Silva laid siege to this site and constructed a massive siege ramp completed in 73 CE. (20 pts)",
        "Josephus wrote of two speeches that a Sicari leader made at this site convincing his men to kill themselves. Herod the Great built two palaces for himself at this site, which was besieged following the First (10 pts)",
        "Jewish War. For ten points, name this fortress captured by the Roman army in the Judaean Desert, which overlooks the Dead Sea."
      ],
      "answer": "Masada 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 2"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1948, one of this sea’s many islands, which is now part of the mainland, became the site of a secret bioweapons facility. In the early 1960s, the Amu Darya and Syr Darya rivers were diverted from this sea to provide desert (20 pts)",
        "irrigation in support of the burgeoning Uzbek cotton farming industry. The Dike Kokoral dam was completed in 2005 in an attempt to replenish this sea’s (10 pts)",
        "diminishing water level. For ten points, name this sea, whose drainage basin encompasses nearly 600,000 square miles in Central Asia."
      ],
      "answer": "Aral Sea"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Shaul Ladany warned people of this event of which \"Issa\" and \"Tony\" were the leaders. The codeword “Sunshine” was supposed to be used during an attack in this event. Andre Spitzer was clubbed in view of cameras during this event. Because of this event, (20 pts)",
        "GSG 9 was created and Ahmed Bouchiki was accidentally killed in Lillehammer, Norway. Israel launched Operation (10 pts)",
        "Wrath of God to target perpetrators of this event which Abu Daoud might have planned for Black September. Occurring at the 1972 Olympics, for ten points, name this massacre of Jewish athletes."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Munich Massacre",
        "Black September Massacre before mentioned",
        "1972 Olympics Massacre before mentioned",
        "\"Kidnapping,\" \"Killing,\" and other words that indicate knowledge of the violence perpetrated in place of Massacre"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Donald Trump circumvented this act by using \"Schedule F appointments\" when he signed an October 2020 Executive Order, an act being described by political scientists as “open cronyism.” The Franklin Pierce administration developed a predecessor to this act by creating a (20 pts)",
        "civil service exam for Cabinet staff. Deranged office seeker Charles J. Guiteau's assassination of President James Garfield led to (10 pts)",
        "reformers pushing this act through in 1883. For ten points, name this civil service reform that attempted to weaken the spoils system in American politics."
      ],
      "answer": "Pendleton Civil Service Reform Act"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This woman earned a PhD from Columbia’s Department of Public Law and Governance and became a professor at Georgetown in 1982. When introducing Hillary Clinton in 2016, this woman said, “There is a special place in hell for (20 pts)",
        "women who don’t help each other.” In 2012, this woman had a tense meeting with a group of activists from her homeland as a result of her role in the NATO bombing of Serbia. This native of (10 pts)",
        "Czechoslovakia was nominated to her highest post by President Bill Clinton. For ten points, name this woman, the first female Secretary of State."
      ],
      "answer": "Madeleine Albright 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 2"
    }
  ]
}